Guide to the Christopher Phillips Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- 1968-1972: Yale Professors, Series IV
  - Arthur F. Wright writings: his draft chapter on the Sui Dynasty for The Cambridge History of China; typescript, 1971? (Box 22, Folder 6)
  - Arthur F. Wright, personal: correspondence, including after graduation; an image of his very patrician car [a Rover sedan, one of my British favorites from childhood]; directions to his house, at Sachem's Head, Guilford, Connecticut; his quoted comments on Mao in The Yale Daily News; his obituary in The Journal of Asian Studies, 1977, with commemorative poem in Chinese calligraphy by James T.C. Liu; description of Arthur F. Wright in Alex Kerr's book Lost Japan [see Series III, 1970-71, for explanation and notes about Alex Kerr]; typescript page of lecture or chapter that is unidentified but sounds a lot like Arthur F. Wright's style; short personal note, written by me in January 2005, about Arthur F. Wright, 1968- (Box 22, Folder 7)
  - Mary Clabaugh Wright [1917-70]: course outline, reading list and list of reserve library books for her undergraduate course China Since 1600 [History 45b], spring 1969; a course paper by me for this class, with her note of agreement with a reader's evaluation, the only Honors grade [Yale equivalent of an A] I ever got in anything; her OK to a combined B.A.-M.A. scheme I devised for myself but never actually did; a get-well letter I wrote to her in her final illness, 1970; obituaries from The New York Times and The Yale Daily News; program from her memorial service at Yale, October 2, 1970; a short personal note by me written in January 2005; a notebook I kept in her History 45b class, though many of the lectures are by other people who substituted for her, 1969-1970 (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - The draft of an imaginary letter to Jonathan D. Spence about Arthur F. Wright and Mary Clabaugh Wright that I wrote in Hong Kong in 1981 as I was about to go into China for the first time. It is a letter I thought about sending from Peking, but did not (Box 23, Folder 9)
  - John Whitney Hall [1916-97]: outline and reading list for his undergraduate Japanese history course [History 44a] and partial list for the postgraduate seminar that ran parallel to it [History 264a]; his written comments on two of my essays for the graduate seminar; his booklet Japanese History: New Dimensions of Approach and Understanding, second edition, 1966, published by American Historical Association; his obituary from The New York Times, 1970- (Box 23, Folder 10)
  - Samuel E. Martin: his written comments on three of my freshman papers for his undergraduate course The Structure of Language [Linguistics 20], 1968-1969 (Box 23, Folder 11)
  - Richard Barnhart: outline and slide list for his course History of Chinese Art [History of Art 70b], 1970 spring (Box 23, Folder 12)
  - Harry J. Benda: his written comments on a paper of mine, "The Role of the Japanese Occupation of Malaya in the Weakening of British Rule," for his Modern Southeast Asian history course [History 72b], 1971 May (Box 23, Folder 13)
  - John K. Whitmore: course outline, reading list and research topics for graduate seminar in Modern Vietnamese history [History 275b], 1971 spring (Box 23, Folder 14)
  - Howard R. Lamar: course outline and reading list for his course The Trans-Mississippi West [History 37a], 1971 fall (Box 23, Folder 15)
  - Other course outlines and/or reading lists, some of them partial: Richard Warch, Popular Culture [American Studies 92-3b], spring 1972; "Mr. Bernstein," Chinese Politics [Political Science 68a], fall 1969; D. Robinson, African History [History 70a], fall 1971; Benjamin Cohen, Economics of Underdeveloped Countries [Economics 74b], 1971, first page only from reading list; "Mr. Garvin," Neighborhood Planning, partial outlines for games with role-playing: Designing a Shopping Center and Renewing Mid-Town Manhattan, 1969-1972 (Box 23, Folder 16)
- June 1972 - June 1973, New York, then Edinburgh (via Paris and London): Starting Out in Life – With Benjamin Sonnenberg and Virgin Records, Series V
  -- June 1972, I graduated from Yale.
  -- June-August 1972, I worked as private secretary to Benjamin Sonnenberg (1901-78), a figure of legend in New York and one of the inventors of modern public relations, in his two adjoining mansions on Gramercy Park. It was my first 9-to-5 job.
  -- September 3, 1972, I went to Paris to seek my fortune, which I did not find there.
  -- October 1972, on a visit to London, I found a job with Virgin Records, which was then a very young company expanding extremely rapidly; my immediate boss was Nik Powell, Richard Branson's second in command (and today a famous movie producer). They sent me to Edinburgh to find premises for a shop and then renovate, open and run it. I worked for Virgin in London for a few weeks, then moved to Edinburgh on November 6, 1972, staying there until May 1973.
  -- December 19, 1972, my 22nd birthday, "my" Virgin Records shop opened at 61 Thistle Street, in the 18th-century New Town district of Edinburgh. I found a furnished flat in the same building two floors up in the front; it was my first apartment.
  -- Fall 1973 to spring 1973, while living in Edinburgh, I was active in gay liberation organizing.
  -- March 7-10, 1973, my parents and their friend T. Margaret Jamer (1901-98, known as Jimmie Jamer) visited me in Edinburgh.
  -- March 28, 1973, my father died.
  -- In spring of 1973, I was making future plans for graduate school in economics and "Pacific urban planning" at the University of Hawaii, to begin in the fall of 1974. Before I could apply, I needed summer courses in economics, and since Edinburgh was freezing cold, I chose the University of California at Los Angeles. To sit out the year between my application and the start of school, I sought and found teaching jobs at British "prep" schools (boarding schools for boys 9-12).
  -- May 1973, I left Edinburgh for Los Angeles and UCLA. I soon became involved with the Gay Community Services Center and stayed in Los Angeles.
  PERSONAL AND LARGER THEMES
  -- Benjamin Sonnenberg (1901-78), the famous New York public relations man, legendary host, and New York's self-invented "last Edwardian." Includes some details of life in his two adjoining mansions on Gramercy Park, photographs (photocopies) of the houses, and the two Sotheby's catalogues from his estate sale.
  -- Virgin Records, then a very young company, during its period of very rapid expansion, 1972-73. The establishment of Virgin Records, Edinburgh.
  -- Gay organizing in Edinburgh and gay life there.
  -- Some stray bits of gay information from New York, Paris and London.
  -- Examples of how gay people copied down names, contact information and other resources in the days when this information was hard to find, before the Internet or readily available gay guides or periodicals.
  -- A young man's search for a place in the world, first in Paris, then London and finally Edinburgh. I was loosening up more in this period, a shift symbolized by my return to Britain, not as a church musician, but as part of – though an ill-fitting part of – the hip counterculture as symbolized by Virgin Records.
  -- Learning in Edinburgh an important lesson about my far-flung schemes: one can assemble the perfect job and perfect apartment in the perfect city, and those do not necessarily add up to a happy life.
  -- More of my tendency to think big and wide-screen: I was sitting in Edinburgh making plans for Los Angeles and Honolulu.
  -- Running before I could walk. Though I told Virgin Records I knew nothing about rock music or running a shop, they plunged me in at the top. This is a continuing theme in these papers: I started my journalism career as managing editor of a magazine (Taiwan 1975-76 Series) and started my book publishing house without any experience in the field (Israel 1984-87 and London 1987-91 Series).
  -- The last gasp of my interest in British boarding schools. This time they were not a fascination but a means to sit out the year while I applied to graduate school. At this time I had my last contacts with Anthony Chenevix-Trench, who had moved from being headmaster of Eton to Fettes College in Edinburgh.
  -- The workings of the Gabbitas-Thring Services of Sackville Street, Mayfair, London, famous for placing those at a loose end in jobs in private schools throughout Britain and the world. I had the feeling that this place was every well-bred young man's greatest comfort and greatest fear.
  -- Gay files (7).
  1) In this series I have grouped together all material relating to Benjamin Sonnenberg, Virgin Records and gay life in Edinburgh, even if that meant some lapses in chronology.
  2) For the address book I used during this period, see June 1971.
  3) One carton of my archives from this period got lost in transit from Edinburgh to Los Angeles.
  4) Most dates follow British usage (day/month/year), though I went back and forth between British and American systems in my personal writings.
  - Relevant pages in my passport for this period, prior to my obtaining a new passport in January 1973 [photocopies: the original are in Series III], 1972-1973 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - New York, summer after graduation: correspondence and activities, 1972 June-August (Box 24, Folder 2)
  - Gay, New York: Gay Revolution Networker newsletter; card from a bar, The Original Danny's "Where It Happened First," 139 Christopher Street, Greenwich Village, 1972 June-August (Box 24, Folder 3)
  - Benjamin Sonnenberg [1901-78]: memo to me from Jeanette Blader, his longtime private secretary, before she went on vacation, about the running of his operation and his two mansions on Gramercy Park, including things to remind him of [five pages typewritten, plus some 3 x 5 cards, address labels and enclosure cards]; my memos to him about my arrangement of the books in his library; memo about book arrangement before my arrival, with diagram; one of Benjamin Sonnenberg's printed notepads; a blank 1955 British pocket date book that he was throwing away, with his initials stamped in gold, 1972 summer (Box 24, Folder 4)
  - Benjamin Sonnenberg: press coverage after his death; detailed history of his house at 19 Gramercy Park, the former Stuyvesant Fish house, with renovations by McKim, Mead & White; photographs (photocopies?) of the house taken by Billy Cunningham [New York interiors photographer, not to be confused with Bill Cunningham of The New York Times ]; photocopies of jackets of a biography of Benjamin Sonnenberg and of a memoir by his son, Benjamin Sonnenberg Jr., founder of Grand Street magazine; an article about Benjamin Sonnenberg Jr.; photocopy of opening page of the Benjamin Sonnenberg chapter in Brendan Gill's 1990 memoir A New York Life, 1978-1991 (Box 24, Folder 5)
  - Benjamin Sonnenberg Collection: Sotheby's New York sale catalogue: two volumes, 1979 June 5-9 (Box 24, Folder 6-7)
  - Memos that Benjamin Sonnenberg asked me to write outlining my hopes for a first career step: includes draft of a letter of introduction he asked me to write for presentation to friends of his in Paris; it shows my thinking at the time about what I had to offer and what I wanted, 1972 August (Box 24, Folder 8)
  - Keepsakes from my mother on my departure for Paris: her "plane letter" [letter to be read on journey] and her flyleaf inscription in a book she gave me, 1972 Aug; September 3 (Box 24, Folder 9)
  - Paris, letters to and from me, 1972 September 3-October 16 (Box 24, Folder 10)
  - Paris, my life there: includes the ad I placed in The International Herald Tribune and the responses; also a rough calendar, 1972 September 3-October 16 (Box 24, Folder 11)
  - Gay, Paris: my letter to make contact with Gay Liberation Front in Paris (F.H.A.R.), and their answer, by mail, giving me yet another address to write to; Gay Liberation Front flier; address of Gay Liberation Front that I took with me from the States, including a note of the title of a radical French gay book, 1972 September 3-October 16 (Box 25, Folder 12)
  - Gay, London: Gay Liberation Front, list of five chapters with their meeting places [cut out of a newsletter]; 3 x 5 card with London Gay Liberation Front contact address that I think I copied down in Paris. This information was very hard to find at the time, 1972 October (Box 25, Folder 13)
  - My early days at Virgin Records in London: letters to me, and letters home from me about my new job and plans; Virgin Records material, including price lists; tongue-in-cheek Virgin customer survey with mail-order list; notes I made to learn names of rock bands and record labels; sheets with Japanese vocabulary, in case I needed it in connection with possible international duties at Virgin, which never materialized; early Virgin stationery, complete with misprints; a couple of other bits and pieces from this transitional period, 1972 October 16-November 6 (Box 25, Folder 14)
  - Virgin Records, my trip to Edinburgh to find premises for the new shop: these papers and notes were in the black alligator-skin folder with red satin lining that I carried on the trip, 1972 October 19-20 (Box 25, Folder 15)
  - Virgin Records, Edinburgh, renovating the premises at 61 Thistle Street and preparing to open the shop: includes the contents of the black folder I always carried; renovation documents and notes; ephemera from that period, 1972 November 6-December 19 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - Virgin Records, Edinburgh, running the shop: includes ephemera, some record orders and price lists [more ordering notes are in my appointment book], 1972 December-1973 May (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - Virgin Records, Edinburgh, developments at the shop after my departure, plus some notes about my car and my boxes of files, which I left with friends: letter from Donnie MacRitchie, my assistant at Virgin Records, sent to me in Los Angeles, 1973 July 2 (Box 25, Folder 18)
  - Gay, Scotland: brochure and newsletter from Scottish Minorities Group [S.M.G.]; book of poems by Hannah P. Rogers, an Edinburgh gay group member, and an invitation to her party; Hannah and her American girlfriend Kathy Kiernan's addresses in the U.S.A.; note left for me by a New York gay guy; lapel button from Edinburgh University Gay Group; Christmas card; title page from the book Portrait of a Marriage, which was extremely important when it was published, in 1973. [For notes of some of my gay activities, see also "Edinburgh Chronology (Finally): January 1-March 5, 1973" in this series], 1972 November-1973 (Box 25, Folder 19)
  - Gay, Scotland: Edinburgh University Student newspaper [February 22, 1973] with double-page spread, Homosexuality in Edinburgh. It includes an interview with me and article by Michael Coulson, who worked with me in gay organizing; handwritten notes by me, dated February 5, 1973, for a gay liberation talk I gave to Scottish Minorities Group [S.M.G.]. Both give a good picture of my radical "line" on gay liberation, 1973 February (Box 25, Folder 20)
  - Gay, Edinburgh, developments after I left: photocopies of a letter to me from Michael Coulson of Scottish Minorities Group [S.M.G.]; letter from Rod Hall, 1974; photocopy of an August 1973 letter from me to Michael Coulson written from the Gay Community Services Center, Los Angeles; article from Gay Times newspaper, November 1984, about gay life in Edinburgh, with photograph of Ian Dunn, who was a prominent gay activist there in my era and beyond, 1973-1984 (Box 25, Folder 21)
  - Edinburgh, letters to and from me, 1972 November-1973 May (Box 25, Folder 22-24)
  - Edinburgh, my life there: includes photograph (photocopy) of me behind the cash register in my Virgin Records shop, 1972 November-1973 May (Box 25, Folder 25)
  - Lynn MacRitchie, unpublished novel, The Low Road [1987], describing Edinburgh life at this period: her husband at the time, Donnie MacRitchie, was my assistant at Virgin Records. Lynn MacRitchie, now an artist in London, has remained a close friend and figures in later series in this archive, 1972 November-1973 May (Box 26, Folder 26)
  - Appointment book: includes some Virgin Records ordering information, 1973 January-April (Box 26, Folder 27)
  - "Edinburgh Chronology (Finally): January 1-March 5, 1973": notes made by me in the U.S.A. on December 31, 1973, probably to fill in gaps in diaries; includes gay activities. Some days are not accounted for here. [These are quick notes written New Year's Eve to get them down on paper in some form or another before I forgot; some are hard to read, but I will interpret if requested], 1973 January 1-March 5 (Box 26, Folder 28)
  - Passport #4, issued in New York during my quick January 22-28 visit there, 1973 January 24-1978 (Box 26, Folder 29)
  - My classic car in Edinburgh: 1961 Sunbeam Rapier sedan: brochure, papers and ephemera, 1973 February-May (Box 26, Folder 30)
  - Visit to me in Edinburgh by my parents and their friend T. Margaret Jamer [1901-98, known as Jimmie Jamer]: includes pages from Jimmie's diary covering those days; their itinerary and relics from their trip, which started in the Sychelles and Sri Lanka; my father's last letter to me, in which he described what the visit meant to him, 1973 March 7-10 (Box 26, Folder 31)
  - Death of my father, Samuel J. Phillips, M.D. [April 4, 1916-March 28, 1973]: program from one of his memorial services, at the Unitarian Universalist Fellowship of Huntington, Long Island; program from the dedication of the Sam Phillips Memorial Garden at the fellowship in 1975; an article he wrote for a medical journal about his philosophy of seeing the person in the patient; a cartoon by him; some letters of condolence; ephemera; eerily coincidental letter I sent to my father on March 24 but which arrived after his death; some of my favorite photographs (photocopies) of him and a caricature portrait that captures him very well, 1973 March-1975 (Box 26, Folder 32-33)
  - Seeking teaching jobs in England for 1973-74: résumés and correspondence, including with Gabbitas-Thring Services, individual schools, Anthony Chenevix-Trench [my headmaster at Eton, by this time at Fettes College, Edinburgh], and O.J. Wait [my house master from School House, Mill Hill School]; includes an explanatory note by me, 1973 March-May (Box 26, Folder 34)
- June 1973 - August 1975, Los Angeles (With an Interlude in Alabama): Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective, Series VI
  -- May 1973, I left Edinburgh for New York, where I picked up my car in storage and drove to Los Angeles.
  -- June 1973, I arrived in Los Angeles for summer school in economics at the University of California at Los Angeles; it was my first time in Southern California, and I lived in the dorms.
  -- On June 21, 1973, I went to volunteer at the Gay Community Services Center, then in its first home, in three wooden Victorian houses at 1614 Wilshire Boulevard, at Union Street, just east of MacArthur Park.
  -- Late summer 1973 until August 1974, I worked full time as a "core staff member" of the Gay Community Services Center; most of my work was in the Self Development Program, doing counseling, leading groups and staffing the 24-hour telephone hotline.
  -- Fall 1973, a group of center workers got together to form the Highland Park Collective (in the Highland Park neighborhood, between downtown and Pasadena), which lasted until about 1977, although by then the residents were no longer connected with the center. This collective soon attained near-mythic status in gay Los Angeles history. We moved in on October 1, 1973.
  -- Spring 1974, Ed Sanders arrived from Alabama to work at the Gay Community Services Center. We became a couple, and it was the first time I had actually made a complete life with someone. He moved in with me at the Highland Park Collective.
  -- Early summer 1974, I took a wonderful Chinese language class at open-enrollment Los Angeles City College, with Professor Tung Cheng, an inspiring and elegant man with beautiful Chinese handwriting. He got me back on the Chinese trail.
  -- August-December 1974, Ed Sanders and I went to Tuscaloosa, Alabama, where he was finishing up his Master of Social Work degree at the University of Alabama. I worked as a laborer on the paint crew at Bryce Hospital, the famous ante-bellum state mental hospital in Tuscaloosa. During this time I began making serious plans to continue with East Asian Studies, and these included an idea to go to Asia with Eddy accompanying me in a teaching job.
  -- January-August 1975, Ed Sanders and I were back in Los Angeles. We lived at first in the Eagle Rock neighborhood, moving back to the Highland Park Collective in the summer. During this period Eddy was very involved with the center. I worked there a little, but was mostly studying Chinese and making plans to go to Asia, and actually at something of a loose end. I also took my one and only journalism class, at Los Angeles City College, on news writing, which formed the basis of my whole subsequent career. Also during this period I did some interviews and research in Asian-American Studies, specifically, Japanese-American relocation during World War II. This was a toe in the water in terms of journalism.
  -- Spring 1975, the Gay Community Services Center moved from 1614 Wilshire Boulevard to larger quarters at 1213 North Highland Avenue in Hollywood. As the center grew and started to get more grant funding for its programs, there was discontent within radical sectors of the gay community, including current and former center workers. The result was a "strike" against the center that reached the brink of violence and caused a split within the gay community that continues to be devastating to many people even decades later. (Gay researchers note: this incident is highly important.)
  -- Spring-summer 1975, I worked in a county-funded study at the center called the Alcoholism Needs Assessment project, which investigated whether the primacy of bars in the gay community had led to a strikingly high level of alcohol consumption among gay men. I consider this to be my first editing job.
  -- On August 13, 1975, I left for Taiwan.
  -- Gay: most files relate to gay life, except for the ones labeled Asian-American.
  -- Life in Los Angeles, 1973-75.
  -- Gay life in Los Angeles, 1973-75.
  -- Gay life in New York.
  -- Gay life in isolated parts of the country, as shown in letters written to the center in the days before the Internet.
  -- Gay Community Services Center in its early days -- a great deal of material about the institution, its programs, services and people, who included Don Kilhefner, Morris Kight, Dr. Betty Berzon, Rand Schrader and Sheldon Andelson.
  -- Highland Park Collective, 1973-75, a gay collective made up of center workers. The collective included two people who figure prominently in later series in the archive, Jerome Gold (then known as Crickett Bon Bon) and Jeff B. Richards.
  -- Very brief notes on two other important gay collectives in Los Angeles: the Hoover Street Collective, which was a precursor of Highland Park and home to some of the center's founders; and the Echo Park Collective, whose residents were not involved with the center, and was concurrent with Highland Park.
  -- Documentation that the 12-step group called Sexual Compulsives Anonymous existed in Los Angeles as early as 1973.
  -- Gay history-writing of the early 1970's.
  -- Gay and feminist bibliographies of the early 1970's.
  -- Life in Alabama, 1974.
  -- Bryce Hospital, Tuscaloosa, Alabama: some material about mental health and personnel policies at this state mental hospital.
  -- East Asian Studies, including course offerings in the United States and some foreign countries.
  -- Asian-American Studies programs in the early days of the field.
  -- Asian-American community resources in Los Angeles.